<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at White-hall, March 3, 1694/5, upon occasion of Her late Majesties death before the Right Honourable the Countess of Derby, and the rest of the mourning ladies / by Nicholas Brady ... ; published at the request of that honourable audience.</title>
            <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16219539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16219539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1088:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at White-hall, March 3, 1694/5, upon occasion of Her late Majesties death before the Right Honourable the Countess of Derby, and the rest of the mourning ladies / by Nicholas Brady ... ; published at the request of that honourable audience.</title>
                  <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title page reads: Mr. Brady's sermon at White-hall, upon occasion of the Queens death.</note>
                  <note>Title within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James I, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:105120:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>BRADY's</hi> SERMON AT <hi>WHITE-HALL,</hi> Upon occaſion of the Queens Death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105120:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105120:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at WHITE-HALL, <hi>March</hi> 3. 1694/5. Upon Occaſion of Her Late Majeſties Death;</p>
            <p>BEFORE THE Right Honourable the Counteſs of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> and the reſt of the Mourning Ladies.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nicholas Brady,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of <hi>St. Catherine Cree-Church,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of that Honourable Audience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Parker,</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> under the Piazza of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105120:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105120:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ELIZABETH, Counteſs of DERBY, Groom of the Stole to her late Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe many undeſerved favours I have received from your Ladyſhip, and the dependance which I have upon your Illuſtrious Brother, exact the largeſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments that I am capable of making, and give you a juſt title to whatever I can call
<pb facs="tcp:105120:4"/>mine. But you have ſtill a more peculiar right to the following Diſcourſe, which was preached and publiſhed by your expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, occaſioned by that loſs in which you ſhare ſo greatly; and deſigned to aſſwage that exceſſive Sorrow, which a reflection upon it was too apt to excite, in ſo true a Mourner as your Ladyſhip. I queſtion not, but that greatneſs of Soul, and firmneſs of Mind, which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to the blood from which you are deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, together with that exemplary and unaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Piety, which recommended you to the Friendſhip of the beſt of Princeſſes, will now give you their Aſſiſtance when you moſt need it; and enable you to ſupport that Tryal with moderation, which would oppreſs a weaker Courage, and break a Spirit leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned. For your Ladyſhip <hi>has not ſo learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt,</hi> as to ſtruggle ineffectually <hi>under the Croſs,</hi> when he is pleaſed to lay it on; or to think, that infinite Wiſdom and unbound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:105120:4"/>Goodneſs can deal hardly by us, let the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations which encompaſs us be never ſo great; ſuch indeed was that unſpeakable affliction, with which God has lately been pleaſed to viſit us: the ſudden and unexpected loſs of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who was not only <hi>the delight of the Eyes,</hi> but <hi>the Joy too of the Hearts</hi> of all her Subjects; a Princeſs whoſe Character I dare not attempt, for fear of leſſening it; in whom the Conjugal affection of the <hi>firſt Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s <hi>Eleanor,</hi> the undaunted magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>third Edward</hi>'s <hi>Philippa,</hi> with the Religious Zeal, and prudent Government of our late famous <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> were happily uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and improved; and to whom <hi>King Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi>'s Eulogy might juſtly be applied, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Daughters have done Vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi> But whither is my indiſcreet Zeal tranſporting me? faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enumerate ſome few of thoſe Graces, with which your Ladyſhip were ſo intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted,
<pb facs="tcp:105120:5"/>in all their Variety and Perfection? My preſent buſineſs is that of a Comforter, not a Condoler. And if the following diſcourſe can furniſh your Ladyſhip, with ſome Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to combate the greatneſs of your Grief, (which in ſuch Hands cannot but be ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) it will highly contribute to the joy and ſatisfaction, of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladyſhips moſt Obedient, and moſt Obliged Humble Servant,</hi> N. Brady.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105120:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>James I. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>My Brethren, count it all joy, when ye fall into divers temptations.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>LEſt the ſharpneſs and ſeverity of our late af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, which is not confined within the bounds of theſe Kingdoms, but ſheds its influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence over the greateſt part of Chriſtendom, and takes them in for our Fellow-mourners;) Leſt this (I ſay) ſhould tempt us to murmur and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, to exceed the juſt bounds of moderation and prudence, and to quarrel at the unſearchable diſpenſations of an all-good and all-wiſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; I have therefore choſen to entertain you at the preſent, with ſome ſuch ſeaſonable and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meditations, as may direct us to be eaſie under the moſt grievous circumſtances; and by a happy kind of Chriſtian Alchymy, to turn Judgments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Bleſſings. And indeed, there is nothing in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105120:6"/>which men are more generally miſtaken, than in the wrong Notions they uſually entertain, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the various diſpenſations of Providence in this world: becauſe Proſperity carries with it preſent Satisfaction, and is ſet off with a little Tinſel bravery, they are apt to magnifie and admire it; and are as prone to decry and vilifie Adverſity, becauſe it is accompanied with ſome ſenſible un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſſes, and has no gay Pageantry to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it. Whilſt men will thus take up with outſides and appearances, and ſuffer their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments only to play upon the ſurface of things, it will be hard to perſwade them, That the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe is commonly a ſnare, being follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a train of moſt dangerous conſequences; and that the latter is frequently a Bleſſing, being happily attended with conſiderable Advantages: Yet to him that examines things calmly and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, this ſeeming Paradox will be evidently made out; and the Apoſtle will appear to have very good grounds, for exhorting all Chriſtians to rejoyce and triumph, when they find themſelves encompaſſed with manifold afflictions; not only to undergo them with ſuch a ſtedfaſt firmneſs and ſerenity of mind, as ſome of the Heathen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105120:6"/>Philoſophers applauded and attained to; but to carry their Reſignation to a pitch much higher, to which nothing but Chriſtianity could ever yet arrive, by finding juſt matter of Joy and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, in thoſe miſconſtrued occaſions of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and uneaſineſs: <hi>My Brethren,</hi> ſays he, <hi>count it all joy, when ye fall into divers temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words afford us this ſingle propoſition, which I deſign for the ſubject of my following Diſcourſe, namely, That whatſoever afflictions may at any time befall us, if we conſider them duly as Chriſtians ſhould do, they afford juſt matter of Joy and Conſolation.</p>
            <p>The truth of this aſſertion will undeniably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, from theſe three following conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the Nature of our Temptations or Afflictions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From Gods deſign in Expoſing us to them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, From the Conſequences which attend them.</p>
            <p>Firſt Then, from the Nature of our Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Afflictions it will evidently appear, that whenſoever they befall us, if we conſider them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105120:7"/>duly, as Chriſtians ſhould do, they afford juſt matter of Joy and Conſolation.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if we are unaſſiſted by Grace and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if we are left to our ſelves to wreſtle with afflictions, the Natural Man is unable of himſelf to extract Honey out of Wormwood, or to make ſuch Bitter Potions become ſweet and palatable; but if we bring them to the Bar of Religion, and try them by the Laws and Maxims of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we ſhall find all their uneaſineſs to drop off and fall away, and to be happily ſucceeded by comfort and ſatisfaction. All thoſe troubles and afflictions which touch men moſt ſenſibly, and are the moſt likely means to diſturb and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, may be reduced under theſe ſix heads; The Loſs of Reputation, the Loſs of Riches, the Loſs of Liberty, the Loſs of Friends or of Relations, the Loſs of Health, and the Loſs of Life: Under theſe may be comprehended all manner of Temptations; and if we examin them ſeverally and diſtinctly, we ſhall ſee this Doctrine verified in each particular of them, that they afford us juſt matter of Joy and Conſolation.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Then as to the Loſs of Reputation; This indeed is looked upon by the Natural Man, as a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105120:7"/>very ſharp and grievous misfortune; it makes him mean and contemptible in the eyes of the World, to which he chiefly deſires to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and approve himſelf; it expoſes him to ſlights and diſreſpects; all men ſhun and avoid his ſociety, as if his Infamy were infectious, and think it baſe and ſcandalous to be ſeen to converſe with him: he is the common theme of abuſive Tongues, the mark of malicious Eyes, and <hi>the putting forth of the finger;</hi> and the beſt that he can hope for, is to be ſo far deſpiſed, as at length to be forgotten and diſregarded: This is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which ſeems ſo deplorable, that we have reaſon to call Chriſtianity to our aid, to enable us to ſupport it with any tolerable ſatisfaction; but how ſoon will that plain all the roughneſs and unevenneſs, and make this rugged proſpect appear ſmooth and level! That will repreſent to us, That Credit and Reputation in <hi>this world, are</hi> generally the portion of <hi>the children of it;</hi> That <hi>if we were of this world, the world would love us, and ſpeak well of us;</hi> That all the malicious Reflections it can caſt upon us, are but ſo many proofs of our eſtrangement from it; and ſhall we then be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>that the lot is fallen to us in a fairer ground,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105120:8"/>and that we are entitled to a more goodly heritage?</hi> For this very reaſon it is, that our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us <hi>to rejoyce and be exceeding glad, when men revile us and perſecute us</hi> with their Tongues, <hi>and ſpeak all manner of evil againſt us,</hi> becauſe this was the condition of good men in all ages, <hi>ſo dealt they with the Prophets which were before us;</hi> a Chriſtian will conſider when he is thus afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he either ſuffers by his own fault, or by that of others; if by his own, he may be ſorry for his fault, but ought to rejoyce and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in his ſufferings; ſince theſe are his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonements to God for his offences, and the means of removing his anger from him; if his Credit is impaired by the fault of others, he will pity and forgive his malicious Enemies, and rejoyce in the opportunity of exerciſing his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: were he too much wedded to worldly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, it might engage him to <hi>conform himſelf to</hi> the faſhions of <hi>this world,</hi> to make Fame and Reputation the end of his actions, and to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate his deſires and expectations there; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he has all imaginable reaſon to rejoyce, that the world does not uſe him well enough to make him grow fond of it; he will ſatisfie himſelf
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105120:8"/>with the ſenſe of his own Innocency, till God ſhall think fit to vindicate his Reputation; and ſhall eſtabliſh his Credit with his own <hi>Euge,</hi> with a <hi>well done good and faithful Servant,</hi> before the whole Theatre of Heaven and Earth. Thus will the good Chriſtian comfort himſelf under the Loſs of Reputation, rejoycing in the mean time that he is made like unto his Saviour, who <hi>was deſpiſed and rejected,</hi> ſlander'd and reviled; yet chearfully <hi>committed himſelf to God, who judges Righteouſly.</hi> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to the Loſs of Riches: Theſe are much dearer to moſt men than their Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and therefore the loſs of them is more tedious and inſupportable. To theſe the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man is indebted for all the pleaſures and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of Life; for the gratifying of his Sences, and the pleaſing of his Luſts; and for ſuch a man to be deprived of his wealth, is to loſe that upon which he has his only reliance, for making his Life comfortable and delightful; this is the purchaſer of all his Enjoyments, the grand purveyor that makes proviſion for the fleſh; neither can feaſt his appetites, nor keep up his grandeur, nor preſerve his eſteem,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105120:9"/>if this great ſupport of them all be once remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: The Epicure muſt faſt from his delightful Entertainments, and the profuſe Indulging of his ſenſual appetites; the Ambitious muſt be ſtripped of his numerous Train, and the expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing croud of bare-headed Clients; the Vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious muſt part with his darling Applauſe, and that Incenſe of Praiſe which was offered daily: All theſe were the inſeparable Companions of their Riches, and therefore will not fail to drop off with them: and how miſerable muſt the condition of that man be, who has no taſte of any pleaſures but what this world affords, and is at once diſpoſſeſſed of all the Enjoyments of it! But if we turn the Perſpective, and look upon Riches with the Eye of a Chriſtian, how little will theſe magnified objects then appear, and how truly will they ſhrink to their own narrow dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions! He <hi>puts not his truſt in uncertain Riches,</hi> and therefore loſes not his dependance when <hi>they make themſelves wings to fly away from him;</hi> he conſiders that they are nothing but a little Earth, which the Sun has put a price upon by giving it a colour; that they are clogs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances to the aſpiring Soul, which cannot
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105120:9"/>ſo eaſily take its flight, and raiſe it ſelf to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with ſo much droſs about it: he is glad that he is freed from thoſe grand incentives to carnal pleaſures, thoſe harbingers of Sin, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Deſtruction; That the ſnare is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved which is ſo uſually <hi>an occaſion of falling;</hi> and that wealth placed out of his reach, which is oftentimes laid out to buy Repentance: If his Table is adorned leſs plentifully or artificially, he is thereby leſs liable to intemperance and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; if the croud of viſitants is not ſo great as formerly, he is thereby leſs expoſed to Vanity and Pride; if he finds leſs reſpect paid him now than before, he thereby learns how ſlight a foundation the worldling builds upon, and is taught to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour at more durable advantages: Thus does he make his loſs beneficial to him, by improving in <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> which is <hi>the greateſt gain; he has learned</hi> (with the Apoſtle) <hi>in whatſoever ſtate he is, therewith to be content;</hi> and therefore <hi>knows how to be abaſed, as well as how to abound; how to ſuffer need, as well as how to be full:</hi> In a word, he can <hi>bleſs the Lord</hi> with <hi>Job,</hi> for reducing him to that ſtate, <hi>in which he came into the world,</hi> and in which he <hi>muſt go out of it;</hi> and who by withdrawing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105120:10"/>the conveniencies and advantages of this Life, has happily obliged him to contend for a better. But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As to the Loſs of Liberty: Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Riches are things independent of us, and for which we muſt be beholding to ſomething without us; but Liberty is the Birthright of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, we bring our title to it into the world with us, and the loſs of it is a moſt ſenſible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, to him that conſiders it as a Natural Man. To be ſhut up from all delightful ſociety, and to converſe with nothing but Walls and Grates; to forego all our pleaſing Aſſignations, our divertive Journeys and entertaining Walks; to be wholly confin'd to the narrow proſpect which a Priſon window can afford us, and to be blind in a manner to all the world beſides; to ſee no grateful viciſſitude of Seaſons, no chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful variety of the works of Nature: Nay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to be Fetter'd and Chain'd down to the ground, as if we were one piece with the Earth we lie upon, and were growing again to our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Clod. Theſe are conſiderations ſufficient to diſtract any one, that is not furniſhed with the aſſiſtances of Grace and Religion; but let us reflect upon them according to their Dictates,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105120:10"/>and we ſhall find the caſe to be very different: Thoſe Walls and Bars which ſhut in the Chriſtian, ſhut out the temptations and allurements of the World, and are rather his defences than impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments; to him, his Priſon is his bulwark, that ſecures him from thoſe enemies, which would elſe preſs in upon him; his mind, whoſe freedom he only values, enjoys by this a greater liberty; it has nothing to obſtruct, or to divert its flight, but can range in contemplation, without the leaſt diſturbance; his Body indeed is ſhackled and confined, but does not that it ſelf fetter and tye up his Soul? and therefore he that has put that under reſtraint, has only made a priſoner of his Goaler. How well may he rejoyce, that his time is all his own, that he is freed from the neceſſity of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent viſits, from the dangerous temptations of idle Company, and has leiſure to take himſelf to task without any interruption, and to try and examine the very bottom of his Heart! how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate a communion may he keep up with God, who is ſecured againſt all things that may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw him from it! and how happily may he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert a Dungeon into a Temple, by making it the houſe of Prayer and of Praiſes, and having it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105120:11"/>Illuminated with the light of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance! Thus will the Chriſtian turn this afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into matter of Joy; ſince the confinement of his Body is the enfranchiſement of his Soul, and gives that opportunity to act with greater free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. But</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as to the Loſs of Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. This is a Calamity extremely piercing, and which ſeems to juſtifie a ſenſible concern; becauſe it appears to act generouſly on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of others, and does not openly diſcover that Principle of Self-Love, to which however it truly owes its beginning: When this affliction ſurprizes the Natural Man, he judges himſelf without Comfort, becauſe without Remedy; loſt Reputation may be re-eſtabliſhed, loſt Riches may be Recovered, loſt Liberty may be Regained, but the loſs of a Friend or Dear Relation, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all poſſibility of being Retrieved. Muſt he never more enjoy that delightful converſation, that agreeable commerce and familiarity with his Friend? Shall he never more be bleſſed with the tender careſſes of his careful and indulgent Parents? Muſt he for ever be baniſhed from the charming ſociety of his Wife, and the pretty dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105120:11"/>of his hopeful Children? are they paſſed into the Land from whence they never muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn? and has the inexecrable Grave ſhut its Mouth upon them for ever? thus will he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain in the anguiſh of his Soul, who has no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Antidotes againſt ſo great a miſery, but what bare humane reaſon is capable of adminiſtring; he ſees nothing beyond the Grave; Death and the Pit terminate his proſpect; and therefore make up an object all black and melancholly. But the Chriſtian, whoſe Eye can pierce much farther, who can look through this <hi>Darkneſs</hi> into the <hi>land of Light,</hi> conſiders his departed Friends with joy and ſatisfaction: He knows they have got the better of the exchange by being taken out of a miſerable World, to be admitted into a ſtate of Happineſs and Perfection; he prefers their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage before his own enjoyments, and rejoyces at their removal into bliſs, tho he pays dearly for it by his own want of them; he looks upon them as ſo many Harbingers which are gone before him to prepare his way; he <hi>longs to be diſſolved,</hi> and <hi>to go to Chriſt</hi> and them, but cannot be ſo ſelfiſh or uncharitable, as to wiſh them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with him; he is glad that his Companion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105120:12"/>is in a better Society, and that his Friend is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd into an Angel; he conſiders that they are got out of the priſon of the Fleſh, and cannot repine at their Releaſement, tho he is ſtill forced to drag the Chain, and bear about him his earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fetters; he has nothing ſo Dear, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſign to God, or which he can deſire to be better diſpoſed of; he reflects upon the mortality of their condition, and by daily meditating that they muſt once dye, he is enabled to acquieſce in it whenſoever it happens: And ſince he is certain that God orders every thing for the beſt, he chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſubmits to his diſpenſations, and joyfully concurs with the workings of his Providence. Thus will the Chriſtian comfort himſelf, for the loſs of his Friends or his dear Relations, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that they are <hi>in the hands of a merciful Creator,</hi> and letting his own loſs be ſwallowed up in the juſt conſideration of their advantage. But</p>
            <p>Fifthly, as to the Loſs of Health. This is an Affliction of ſuch extraordinary ſharpneſs, that it was reſerved by the Tempter, as his laſt Engine, to batter down the conſtancy of righteous <hi>Job;</hi> when he had ſtood the loſs of his Subſtance, and Relations with an unſhaken patience, yet this he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105120:12"/>ſuppoſed would ſhock his Reſolution: <hi>Skin for skin,</hi> ſays he, <hi>yea all that a man hath will he give for his Life; but put forth thy Hand now, and touch his Bone and his Fleſh, and he will curſe thee to thy Face.</hi> And indeed this maxime (tho uttered by the Father of lies,) carries too much truth with it in Relation to the natural man; for, can any object be more lamentable, than to ſee ſuch a one confined to his ſick Bed? to ſee all outward Comforts withdrawn from him, and nothing within to ſupport or ſuſtain him? when his very Bed becomes a Rack, and he lies there, as if ſtretcht upon the Engine of his Torture; when an Ague chills his Blood, and turns it into Iſicles, or a Fever makes it glow like Liquid Fire; when his Body is covered over with Rottenneſs and Putrefaction, and Coruption has taken poſſeſſion of it on this ſide the Grave! how will he then roar for the diſquietneſs of his Soul, and knows not whether to apply himſelf for Eaſe and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment! Comfort is as much a ſtranger to his heart, as ſleep is to his eves; and the words of conſolation are as taſteleſs and inſipid, as Muſick to his Ears, or rich Wines to his Palate: But to him who has the art of ſanctifying afflictions, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105120:13"/>of breaking their force by a Chriſtian Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all things will put on another ſemblance: Sickneſs, to ſuch a man, is but a different way of mortifying the fleſh, which muſt otherwiſe have been done by humiliation, abſtinence, and ſuch other methods of ſelf-denial; a means to make us weary and out of conceit with this world, to which we are wont to be too fondly devoted: It is a mark of Gods care and paternal love, the correction of a tender and indulgent Father; a ſign that he has not utterly caſt us off, but is willing to draw us to him by one way or other. Here it is that the Chriſtian diſengages himſelf wholly, from the blandiſhments and allurements of this preſent Life; that he gets looſe from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that ſtands between him and heaven, and ſhakes off all the hinderances of his Union with God; his vigorous Soul is juſt upon the wing, and waits impatiently for death to give it its general diſcharge; and while he is thus pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and longing after God, God cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to abſent himſelf from him; <hi>he makes his bed in all his ſickneſs,</hi> ſupplies with his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence all other advantages, and by the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Refreſhings of his Spirit, <hi>he cauſes him to hear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105120:13"/>of joy and gladneſs, and makes the bones which he hath broken to rejoice.</hi> Theſe Conſiderations will ſupport the Chriſtian under the great temptation of ſickneſs and infirmity: Since he is then but treading a rougher path to happineſs, and is ſtill upon his way towards God and Heaven, though the circumſtances of the Road may be tireſome and uneaſie. But,</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, As to the Loſs of Life. This is to the Natural Man the moſt diſtracting and confounding of all afflictions; it for ever puts an end to all his enjoyments; it divorces him from the world, to which he is faſtened and rivetted by all the ties of Intereſt and Inclination; for all the beauteous entertainments of his Senſes, it only preſents him with a univerſal blank; it tears him from his Poſſeſſions, his Friends, and his Relations; he muſt now leave all the engaging en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, all the agreeable ſocieties and diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to which he has been accuſtomed and familiar from his Cradle; and has no proſpect of any ſuitable compenſation for them: To ſuch a Man as this, Death comes arrayed in all his pomp of terror; if he looks upon this world, which he is about to take leave of, he finds that he is parting with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105120:14"/>his deareſt Companion, the delight of all his ſences, and the comfort of his ſoul; if he looks upon that world which he is about to go into, he has made no acquaintances there, ſecured no intereſts, engaged no friendſhips to make his future abode delightful and agreeable; if he is ſo ſtupid and inconſiderate, as to have no proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the miſery that awaits him, yet at beſt he ſees nothing before him, but darkneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, <hi>a Land</hi> of Silence, <hi>where all things are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten:</hi> But the dying Chriſtian who examins things duly, finds ſufficient cauſe of triumph and rejoycing; he has no ſuch intimate engagements with the world, as may render it inſupportable to him to part from it; he has nothing of Earth to hang heavy upon his Soul, or to weigh it downwards to this dull center of corruption; it is long ſince that the world and he took leave of one another, he has a long time been dead unto that, <hi>having mortified his members which were upon the earth;</hi> he can have no regret for parting with that, of which he never entertained any tolerable good opinion, all whoſe advantages he hath found to be but Vanity, and all its entertainments <hi>Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Spirit:</hi> Nay, he reflects upon what he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105120:14"/>is to leave with comfort and ſatisfaction; he parts with nothing but an inveterate Enemy, which has all his Life long been endeavouring to deſtroy him, has ſtill put ſtumbling Blocks in his way to Heaven and Happineſs, and has been miſleading him from the Paths of everlaſting fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; the warfare is accompliſhed, the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties overcome, with which he has always been obliged to encounter, and he is now going to receive the reward of his labours; he is lying down in Peace to take his reſt, with aſſurance of waking to a Joyful Reſurrection; and that King of Terrors appears no otherwiſe to him, than as a grim Meſſenger that comes upon a welcom Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, or a rough guſt of Wind, that blows him into the harbour. After this manner will the ſerious Chriſtian diſarm Death it ſelf of its Sting and of its Terror, by reflecting on it, as the paſſage out of a troubleſome World, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into another of eternal felicity.</p>
            <p>Thus have we viewed the different aſpects, which the ſeveral moſt grevious Temptations put on, according to the various ways in which they may be conſidered; and we may from hence conclude, that however frightful they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105120:15"/>to the natural man, yet to the thoughtful Chriſtian they are matter of Comfort; and if we ſeriouſly reflect upon the nature of afflictions, we have juſt reaſon <hi>to count it all Joy, when we fall into divers temptations.</hi> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the conſideration of Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in expoſing us to afflictions it will evidently appear, that whenſoever they befal us, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon them duly as Chriſtians ſhould do, they afford juſt matter of Joy and Conſolation.</p>
            <p>Afflictions are often thus expreſſed by the name of Temptations, becauſe they are tryals which God vouchſafes us with a gracious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of promoting our advantage: for either he ſees ſomething in us which ought to be corrected, and then God lays his heavy hand upon us, in order to make us reflect upon our errors, and conſequently to qualifie our ſelves for pardon and forgiveneſs; or elſe he has a mind to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our faith and our patience, in order to fit us for the great recompence of reward; and both of theſe deſigns are ſo very beneficial, that they are abundantly ſufficient to make us rejoyce, in the midſt of our troubles and afflictions.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105120:15"/>
            <p> Firſt then, God is ſometimes pleaſed to chaſten and correct us, in order to our amendment.</p>
            <p>Whilſt all things go on ſucceſsfully with us, and we meet with no rubs in the courſe of our affairs, we are apt to be careleſs and neglectful of our duty; but when it pleaſes God to awaken us by adverſity, we then begin to reflect upon our ways, to examin wherein we have offended, what particular tranſgreſſion God is viſiting us for, and what method we ſhould take to regain his favour: <hi>It is good for me</hi> (ſays <hi>David</hi>) <hi>that I have been afflicted, that I might learn thy ſtatutes;</hi> pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as he was, and cautious of his ways, yet want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he ſometimes ſuch a ſevere Remembrancer; <hi>Before I was afflicted</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I went aſtray, but now I have kept thy word:</hi> It is the natural effect of proſperity, to make us ſecure, <hi>to kick with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhurun,</hi> to be puffed up and proud, and <hi>to ſay in our hearts who is the Lord?</hi> But when we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with tryals and afflictions, then we are induced <hi>to call upon the Lord, and to get our ſelves unto our Lord right humbly;</hi> then we are <hi>for putting away the accurſed thing,</hi> for parting with every thing that ſets us at enmity with him; for devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſlaughter our darling Iniquities, <hi>for bringing forth his enemies, that would not have him
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105120:16"/>reign over them, and ſlaying them openly before his face:</hi> And this is one of the great ends which God aims at by afflicting; <hi>he does not delight to grieve the ſons of men,</hi> he takes no pleaſure in the miſeries of his Creatures; but inflicts a leſs pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to ſecure us from a greater, and chaſtiſes us in mercy, to lead us to Repentance. And how then ſhould he rejoyce, that is under theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, when he contemplates upon the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs which God expreſſes herein? how ought he to kiſs the Rod that is laid on with ſo kind and fatherly an intention? how chearfully ſhould he endeavour to anſwer the bleſſed end of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, that ſo <hi>God may be entreated to withdraw his heavy hand,</hi> who notwithſtanding that he ſeems <hi>to hide his face from him, yet has not forgotten to be gracious, nor has ſhut up his loving kindneſs in diſpleaſure.</hi> But</p>
            <p>Secondly, God ſometimes is pleaſed to chaſten and correct us, for the tryal of our Faith, and the exerciſe of our Patience. It is eaſie to pretend that we will rely upon God, that we will put our whole truſt and confidence in him, when nothing more is required to prove that we are real, but our own bare affirming that we are ſo; it is eaſie to believe that God will ſeed and cloath us, when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105120:16"/>our Faith is ſupported by a plentiful Eſtate; it is eaſie to believe that God watches over us, when we enjoy the great advantages of health and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; but when God ſhall ſtrip us bare of all theſe comforts; when hunger and nakedneſs, and ſickneſs and adverſity beſet us round, then to have a Faith that is ſtedfaſt and unmovable in all theſe changes, this is praiſe worthy, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with God: we may think we are willing to depend upon him, but <hi>our hearts</hi> which <hi>are deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful above all things,</hi> may delude us; and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſure of our own Integrity, till we have gone through a Temptation of this nature; he that has paſſed <hi>this fiery Tryal,</hi> and has been thus refined <hi>in the furnace of adverſity,</hi> has then been examined by the trueſt Touchſtone, and has ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently demonſtrated that his Faith is not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit. But as afflictions are ſent for the Tryals of our Faith, ſo alſo are they for the exerciſe of our Patience: This is a Grace which can never be practiced but in the rough Tempeſts of Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it rppears (like the Rain-bow) only in Storms; but is, like that, a ſign of Mercy, and the happy fore-runner of a Calm. When we are poſſeſſed of an influence of all things deſirable, and have nothing that pinches or contradicts our humour,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105120:17"/>it is eaſie for us to comply with the will of God, becauſe we find it ſo conformable then with our own; it is eaſie to be contented with the Divine diſpenſations, becauſe our affairs are then carried on, as if we our ſelves had the diſpoſal of them; but to have our wills reſigned to Gods good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when that thwarts all our Intereſts and all our Deſires; to ſubmit chearfully to whatſoever he impoſes, how contrary ſoever to our own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations; this is ſuch a patience as becomes a Chriſtian, and which God will not fail abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reward: for this is another of his deſigns in viſiting us with afflictions, to wean us from our ſelves, to break our ſtubborn wills, and bend them to the yoak which he would put upon us; and then he will take care, when this end is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, to make <hi>his yoke eaſie and his burthen light,</hi> and the brighteſt Crown of Glory ſhall be then ſet apart, to <hi>reward this faith and patience of the Saints.</hi> Theſe conſiderations of Gods gracious deſigns in all his Inflictions, either to work our amendment by a ſenſe of our unworthineſs, or to encreaſe our recompence for the exerciſe of freſh graces, ſhould buoy up our Spirits under all our Tribulations, and ſhould forcibly perſwade us <hi>to count it all joy, when we fall into divers temptations.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105120:17"/>
            <p> Thirdly and laſtly, From the conſideration of thoſe conſequences which attend our afflictions, it will evidently appear, that whenſoever they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us, if we meditate upon them duly as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould do, they afford us juſt matter of Joy and Conſolation.</p>
            <p>A good Chriſtian is always bettered by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he is improved by ſufferings, and made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect through tryals; he is purified (like Gold,) by paſſing through the fire, his droſs is purged away, and his value made unqueſtionable: Pride, which was the deſtruction of our humane Nature, can find no place in the midſt of Sufferings; and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which is the Ground work of all Chriſtian Graces, is moſt ſucceſsfully advanced and culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated by them; when the heart is made ſoft and tender by adverſity, then is our Charity moſt likely to be enlarged, and we are never more apt to compaſſionate our Brethren, than when we our ſelves are objects of Pity: This gives us a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeling of the miſeries of others, and convinces us how inhumane it is to be unaffected with them, by the ſence which we have of the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our own: This withdraws our dependance from the things of this world, and makes us throw our ſelves for ſuccour entirely upon God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105120:18"/>becauſe it gives us a ſenſible Experience, that he only is able to adminiſter Relief; then is our hope moſt quick and lively, when it has ſo large a field to range in, and that we find our ſelves poſſeſſed of nothing but all things lye open to our expectations; then will the Fleſh be moſt manageable and ſubmiſſive, when all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and Entertainments of it are utterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn; then will the World be leaſt able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us, when we are leaſt involved in its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching vanities, and moſt fully eſtranged from its inviting allurements: Thus will afflictions <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain our Souls, and keep them low, even as a Child that is weaned from its Mother;</hi> and a conſtant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Innocency and Purity, will be one happy conſequence of theſe Temptations. But a greater conſolation than any we have mentioned, is the bleſſed reſult of theſe Calamities, and of that devout temper which is produced by them; and that is the favour and protection of our God; if he takes away from us all other ſupports, it is that we may fly to him only for ſuccour and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtance; and what can more fully recommend us to a merciful Creator, than a view of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which his Creatures lye under, and that ſubmiſs frame of mind to which thoſe have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105120:18"/>them? <hi>they have had their evil things in this world, and therefore ſhall</hi> (like <hi>Lazarus) be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in the other;</hi> whilſt thoſe who (with the Rich Glutton) <hi>had their good things here,</hi> have, unleſs they have uſed them with extraordinary care, the leſs to expect of happineſs hereafter. <hi>Bleſſed then are thoſe that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted; their heavineſs may endure for a night, but joy ſhall come to them in the morning; they may ſow in tears, but they ſhall reap in joy; and he that now goes on his way weeping, and bears forth good ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again with joy, and ſhall bring his ſheaves with him.</hi> Theſe Conſiderations therefore, of the happy conſequences which attend our afflictions, that they make us better in this world, and prepare us to be happier in the next, ſhould powerfully engage us to <hi>count it all joy, when we fall into divers temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us all then, in the name of God, whenever it ſhall pleaſe him to try us with afflictions, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in that heavy one which he has laid upon us at preſent, ſubmit to them with that willingneſs and chearfulneſs of Spirit, that becomes profeſſors of our moſt holy Religion; let us never be diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Natural man is, who being deſtitute of the helps of Grace and Religion, finds nothing in them but ſorrow and diſtreſs; but let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105120:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>that other things are expected from us, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the advantages we ſtand poſſeſſed of: Let us reflect upon the nature of them, as Chriſtians ſhould, and that under all their ſeveral circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whether loſs of Reputation, of Riches, or of Liberty, of our Friends, our Health, or Life it ſelf, and we ſhall find them to be matter of Joy and Conſolation: Let us examin the deſign of Gods inflicting them, and we ſhall find them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to thoſe comfortable ends, of our being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily penitent in this world, and eminently happy in that which is to come: Let us reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſequences which neceſſarily flow from them, and they will appear to be theſe great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Conſtancy and Perfection in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duties, and a reward proportionable to ſuch performances: So ſhall we learn to value afflictions as we ought to ſanctifie and improve them to our comfort and advantage, and to place them amongſt the inſtances of Gods favour and affection; ſo ſhall we be qualified <hi>to count it all joy, when we fall into divers Iemptations.</hi> Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give you a right Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; To him, the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, three perſons but one God, be aſcribed all Honor, Power, Might, Majeſty and Dominion, henceforth and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
